question	option-1	option-2	option-3	option-4	answer
QUESTION PAPER Promotion to Gr.B posts against 70% Quota-AOM [SHIFT - 1] Exam Date : 04/05/2025 Time : 10:00 AM - 12:00 PM Part A Question 1					
"According to G&SR, in MACLS territory, where more than one distant signals are provided, which aspects the Distant signal will be capable of displaying ? सामान्य तथा सहायक िनयमो ंके अनुसार, बहुसंके ती रंगीन रोशनी िसग्निलंग क्षेत्र म जहां एक से अिधक दूर (िडस्टट) िसग्नल मौजूद है वहां दूर (िडस्टट) िसग्नल कौन से संके त दशाता है ?"	Caution or Attention or Proceed	Caution or Proceed	Attention or Proceed	Only Attention	
"In the context of Block working, UFSBI means…. ॉक विक ग के संदभ म, यु एफ एस बी आय (UFSBI) का अथ है..."	Unique Fail Safe Block Instrument	Universal Fail Safe Block Identity	Universal Fail Safe Block Interface	Unique Fail Safe Block Identity	
Which of the following will be classified as serious accident ? िनम्निलखत म से िकसे गंभीर दुघटना के रूप म वगकृ त िकया जाएगा?	2 casualties plus no damage to railway proerty	No casualty plus damage to railway property worth rs 3 cr	3 grievous injury plus no damage to railway property	All of these	
"Which section of the Railways Act, 1989 deals with reportable accidents ? रेलवे अिधिनयम, 1989 की कौन सी धारा रपोट योग्य दुघटनाओ ंसे संबंिधत है?"	Section 110	Section 115	Section 113	Section 120	
"In case of a serious passenger train accident, the central control shall first of all inform… िकसी गंभीर यात्री रेल दुघटना की स्थित म, क द्रीय िनयंत्रण सबसे पहले..... को सूिचत करेगा."	Principal Chief Safety Officer	Principal Chief Medical Director	Secretary to General Manager	Principal Chief Operations Manager	
"Who is responsible for the availability, helpfulness and good conduct of station porters ? स्टेशन पोटरो ंकी उपलब्धता, सहायताशीलता और अे आचरण के िलए कौन िजम्मेदार है?"	Supervisory SM/ Station Manager	Traffic Inspector	Commercial Inspector	Booking Clerk	
Power plan indicates…... पावर योजना दशाित है…...	the maximum number of locos required for freight services section wise.	the minimum number of locos required for freight services section wise.	the number of locos required for freight services in peak loading period.	the daily average number of locos required for freight services section wise.	
"In operating statistics, which is not a Primary Unit? परचालन सांख्यकी म कौन सी प्राथिमक इकाई नही ंहै?"	Duration	Distance	Quantity	Commodity	
Which of the following category of trains does not require ordering ? िनम्निलखत म से िकस ेणी की टेनो ंको ऑडर करने की आवश्यकता नही ंहोती है?	EUR rake	Mixed train	Scheduled M	Container trains	
Which class of ODC can be moved during day and night? ओ.डी.सी. की िकस ेणी को िदन और रात के दौरान चलाया जा सकता है?	Only Class A	Only Class B	Both Class A and Class B	Class C	
"Under which section of the Railways Act, 1989, railway board has been empowered to charge freight over route, which may not be the shortest between loading point and destination ? रेलवे अिधिनयम, 1989 की िकस धारा के तहत रेलवे बोड को उस माग पर माल भाड़ा वसूलने का अिधकार िदया गया है, जो लोिडंग िबंदु और गंतव्य के बीच सबसे छोटा माग न हो?"	Section 71	Section 45	Section 100	Section 20	
"When checking an ESP, how much minimum radius of curve will you accept as per SOD for BG ? ई एस पी जाँच करते समय, ॉड गेज के िलए शेूल ऑफ डाइमशन के अनुसार, गोलाई की ा न्यूनतम ित्रज्या आप स्वीकृ त करगे?"	175 mt	200 mt	100 mt	300 mt	
"In case of ODC, what is the minimum gross clearance from the over head contact wire that can be permitted over electrified section ? ओ.डी.सी. के मामले म, िवद्युतीकृ त खंड पर ओवरहेड संपक तार से न्यूनतम सकल िनकासी ा है िजसकी अनुमित दी जा सकती है?"	200 mm	100 mm	390 mm	340 mm	
One consignment has gross clearance of 7 inches (17.78 cm) from minimum fixed structure profile. What is its ओ डी सी classification ? एक कन्साइनमट म न्यूनतम स्थर संरचना प्रोफ़ाइल से ७ इंच (१७.७८ सेमी) की सकल िनकासी( ग्रॉस क्लीअरंस) है। इसका ODC वगकरण ा है?	B class	A class	C class	Not permitted as ODC	
Which of the following is not a function of Control Office ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा िनयंत्रण कायालय का काय नही ंहै?	Monitoring freight interchange	Arrange relief for overhours crew	Arrange supply of wagons	Waiver of demurrage	
"According to the Disaster Management Plan, what is CBRN ? आपदा प्रबंधन योजना के अनुसार, सी बी आर एन ा है?"	Critical Backup Resource Network	Critical Bottleneck of Railway Network	Chemical Biological radiological Nuclear	None of these	
Which of the following is recognized as disaster within the DMP ? आपदा प्रबंधन योजना के अंतगत िनम्निलखत म से िकसे आपदा के रूप म मान्यता दी गई है?	Train accidents	Natural disasters	Man-made disasters	All of these	
"Under the DMP, which department is responsible for evacuation of people and animals in case of a railway disaster ? डीएमपी के तहत, रेलवे आपदा की स्थित म लोगो ंऔर जानवरो ंको िनकालने के िलए कौन सा िवभाग िजम्मेदार है?"	Operating	Commercial	Mechanical	Safety	
What is the target time for tuning out of ART by day from the time of sounding siren ? सायरन बजने के समय से िदन म एआरटी प्रस्थान का लक्ष्य समय ा है?	30 Minutes	45 Minutes	20 Minutes	60 Minutes	
The average speed of a superfast train is at least.... एक सुपरफास्ट टेन की औसत गित कम से कम....	75 Kmph	65 Kmph	55 Kmph	90 Kmph	
Which of the following affects the section capacity adversely? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा खंड क्षमता पर प्रितकू ल प्रभाव डालता है?	Speed differential	Automatic signalling	Reduction in PSR	Additional loop lines	
The CCRS organization is under the administrative control of.... सीसीआरएस संगठन …... प्रशासिनक िनयंत्रण के अधीन हैI	Ministry of Railways	Ministry of Civil Aviation	Ministry of Urban Development	Ministry of Transport	
Which is the nodal department for procurement of new weighbridges ? नए वे िज खरीदने हेतु नोडल िवभाग कौन सा है ?	Mechanical	Operating	Commercial	Civil Engineering	
"When LC gate is closed & locked, Gate control provided on the SM's control panel shall display…....indicaion. जब समपार फाटक बंद और लॉक हो जाता है, तो एसएम के िनयंत्रण पैनल पर प्रदान िकया गया गेट िनयंत्रण ..... संके त प्रदिशत करेगाI"	Steady Yellow	Steady Green	Steady Red	Flashing Yellow	
"If a signal fails to display any aspect at a location where it is ordinarily shown, the LP should.... यिद कोई िसग्नल िकसी स्थान पर कोई संके त प्रदिशत करने म िवफल रहता है, जहां इसे सामान्यतः िदखाया जाता है, तो एल.पी. …"	Proceed cautiously with whistling	Proceed at 10 Kmph	Bring the train to a halt	Proceed cautiously till the next signal	
"With the latest amendment of Railway Act, 1989, which of the following acts has been repealed ? रेलवे अिधिनयम, 1989 के नवीनतम संशोधन के साथ, िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा अिधिनयम िनरस्त कर िदया गया है?"	"Indian Railway Board Act, 1905"	"Indian Railways Act, 1890"	"Indian Railway Board Act, 1905 and Indian Railways Act, 1890"	None of these	
"What is the minimum length of platform line you will plan to handle 22 coach LHB train plus one VPU plus one loco ?? 22 कोच एलएचबी टेन, एक वीपीयू और एक लोको के परचालन के िलए आप िकतनी न्यूनतम लंबाई की ेटफाम लाइन की योजना बनाएंगे?"	At least 700 mt	At least 500 mt	At least 600 mt	At least 800 mt	
Dispensation for non isolated shunting movements with separation distance of more than 120 mt can be permitted by... सेपरेशन िडस्टस १२० मीटर से अिधक होने की स्थित म नॉन आइसोलेटेड शंिटंग की अनुमित (िडसेशन) ….....ारा दी जा सकती है।	PCOM	PCSO	CRS	GM	
"If gradient is steeper than 1 in 80 falling towards the station section, a ….. is provided to protect the station section. यिद ढलान स्टेशन खंड की ओर 80 म 1 से अिधक तीव्र है, तो स्टेशन खंड की सुरक्षा के िलए .... प्रदान िकया जाता है।"	Trap point	Catch siding	Slip siding	Shunting neck	
How are track circuits bifurcated electrically and physically ? टैक सिक ट को िवद्युतीय और भौितक रूप से कै से िवभािजत िकया जाता है?	By SEJ	BY transverse bonds	By Glued joints	None of these	
What is the purpose of traffic block for de-stressing of track ? टैक को डी स्टेस करने हेतु यातायात ॉक का उेश्य ा है?	Avoid weld failure	Improve drainage	Improve riding	Avoid buckling	
A colour light Distant signal can be combined with the last Stop signal of a station in rear with the approval of…. रंगीन रोशनी िडस्टट िसग्नल को …...की मंजूरी से पीछे के स्टेशन के अंितम रोक िसग्नल के साथ जोड़ा जा सकता है।	GM	CRS	PCOM	PCSO	
Which of the following is not a fixed stop signal for approaching train ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा आने वाली गाड़ी के िलए एक स्थावर रोक िसग्नल नही ंहै?	Outer signal	Home signal	Routing signal	Calling-On signal	
How many high density network (HDN) routes have been identified on IR ? भारतीय रेल पर िकतने उच्च घनत्व नेटवक (एच डी एन) माग की पहचान की गई है?	8	6	7	5	
Which disaster risk reduction framework has been adopted by IR ? भारतीय रेल ारा कौन सा आपदा जोखम न्यूनीकरण ढांचा अपनाया गया है?	Kyoto protocol	Hyogo framework	Sendai framework	None of these	
How much clear maintenance time should be ensured for primary examination of mainline coaching trains ? मेनलाइन कोिचंग टेनो ंकी प्राथिमक जांच के िलए िकतना रखरखाव समय सुिनित िकया जाना चािहए?	4 hrs	6 hrs	8 hrs	5 hrs	
"Expand DCPT In the context of estimation of line capacity utilization over a period of time. िकसी समयाविध म लाइन क्षमता उपयोग के आकलन के संदभ म, डीसीपीटी का िवस्तार कर"	Data Center for Planning Traffic	Digital Capacity Planning Tool	Direct Capacity Planning Table	Digital Capacity for Planning Transportation	
What is the frequency of crew review by the division ? िडवीजन ारा कम दल रव्यू की आवृित्त ा है?	Annual	Monthly	Quarterly	Six monthly	
Which of the following parameter best captures the freight operation performance ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा पैरामीटर माल परचालन िनादन को सवत्तम रूप से दशाता है?	Total interchange	Engine Km per day	NTKm per Wagon Day	WTR	
Which wagon defect is detected by HABD equipment ? एच ए बी डी उपकरण ारा िकस वैगन दोष का पता लगाया जाता है?	Broken spring	Body bulging	Hanging part	Hot axle	
How many TEUs are carried in a fully loaded double stack container rake ? एक पूणतः लोडेड डबल स्टैक कं टेनर रेक म िकतने टी ई यू ले जाए जाते ह?	180	90	45	360	
What is the adequate distance beyond the first stop signal that is required to be kept clear for granting line clear in MACLS territory ? बहु संके ित रंगीन रोशनी िसग्निलंग म लाइन क्लीयर देने के िलए प्रथम रोक िसग्नल से आगे िकतनी पयाप्त दूरी साफ रखना आवश्यक है?	400 mt	180 mt	120 mt	300 mt	
"Under the Gati Shakti Policy, who is the Railway Administration ? गित शक्त नीित के अंतगत रेलवे प्रशासन कौन है?"	GM	DRM	PCOM	RAILWAY BOARD	
Charges levied by Railways on customers for handling of Railway owned rakes at goods sheds are called ….. माल धे पर रेलवे के स्वािमत्व वाले रेको ंकी हडिलंग के िलए रेलवे ारा ग्राहको ंपर लगाए गए शुल्क को ... कहा जाता है।	Land lease charges	Stabling charges	Terminal charges	Terminal access charges	
Who amongst the following is eligible as a GCT operator ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन जीसीटी ऑपरेटर के रूप म पात्र है?	Registerd company	Joint venture	Registered society	All of these	
Which of the following is not essential for ordering a goods train ? मालगाड़ी ऑडर करने के िलए िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा आवश्यक नही ंहै?	Loading demand	Crew availability	Power availability	Path availability	
"Theme based tourist circuit trains introduced by IR , to showcase india's rich cultural heritage and managed by service provider are called…. भारत की समृद्ध सांृ ितक िवरासत को प्रदिशत करने के िलए भारतीय रेल ारा शुरू की गई थीम आधारत पयटक सिक ट टेन, िज सेवा प्रदाता ारा प्रबंिधत िकया जाता है, .....कहलाती हI"	Vande Bharat	NAMO Bharat rapid rail	Bharat Gaurav	Aastha specials	
When a freight train is stabled at a station hand brakes of atleast how many wagons from either end are to be fully tightened ? जब एक मालगाड़ी िकसी स्टेशन पर स्टेबल होती है तो दोनो ंओर से कम से कम िकतने वैगनो ंके हड ेक पूरी तरह कसे जाने चािहए?	6	8	4	2	
"When stabling a consist of three locomotives in a station, hand brakes of which loco should be applied fully ? एक स्टेशन पर तीन इंजनो ंको स्टेबल करते समय, िकस इंजन के हड ेक को पूरी तरह से लगाया जाना चािहए?"	Only leading loco	Only middle loco	Only trailing loco	All the locos	
"Which of the following is a double decker, AC chair car intercity train ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सी डबल डेकर, वातानुकू िलत कु िस यान इंटरिसटी टेन है?"	Yuva exp.	Uday exp.	Tejas exp	None of these	
"Which of the following is an economical, unreserved, superfast Mail/Express service ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सी िकफायती, अनारिक्षत, सुपरफास्ट मेल/एक्सप्रेस सेवा है?"	Humsafar exp.	Antyodaya exp.	Garib rath	None of these	
"A zone has 33 empty BCN on hand at 00.00 hrs. Unloading for the day is 18 BCN and empty receipt forecast is 22 BCN. If the loading for day is 17 BCN, what will be the closing balance of empty BCN? एक जोन म 00.00 बजे ३३ खाली BCN ह। िदन के िलए अनलोिडंग १८ BCN है और पूवानुमान म खाली रसीद २२ BCN है। यिद िदन के िलए लोिडंग १७ BCN है, तो खाली BCN का समापन बैलस ा होगा?"	56	66	46	58	
"According to Preferential Traffic Order, imported coal traffic when sponsored by consignors or coal importers is transported under which priority ? प्रेफरिशयल टैिफक ऑडर के अनुसार ,आयाितत कोयला जब प्रेषक या कोयला आयातक ारा प्रायोिजत होता है तो उसे िकस प्राथिमकता के तहत परवहन िकया जाता है?"	A	B	C	D	
"Under Preferential Traffic Order, who is the accepting authority for POL traffic ? प्रेफरिशयल टैिफक ऑडर के अनुसार, पीओएल यातायात के िलए स्वीकृ ित प्रािधकारी कौन है?"	Railway board	Zonal railway	PCOM	CFTM	
Which stock is used for loading of parcel traffic as deemed VP ? पासल यातायात को डीम्ड वीपी के रूप म लोड करने के िलए िकस स्टॉक का उपयोग िकया जाता है?	NMG	BCN	BOST	VPU	
Which of the following activities cannot be done in CMS ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सी गितिविध ू मैनेजमट िसस्टम म नही ंकी जा सकती?	CTR entry	Reporting of unusual incidents on run	Breathlyser test	RS valve simulation	
Which of the following locos is better suited for operation of heavy trains in graded section ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा लोको ग्रेडेड सेक्शन म भारी टेनो ंके परचालन के िलए बेहतर है?	WAG5	WAG9HH	WAG7	WAG9	
"In planning process, NPG stands for… िनयोजन प्रिया म, एन पी जी का अथ है..."	Network Planning Group	New Project Grant	New Planning Grant	Network Planning Gateway	
Which of the following is not developed by CRIS ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा िस ारा िवकिसत नही ंहै?	ICMS	SATSANG	SFOORTI	KAVACH	
Who is competent to issue special instructions under G and SR ? जी और एसआर के तहत िवशेष िनदश जारी करने के िलए कौन सक्षम है?	CCRS	CRS	GM	PCOM	
"Zonal wagon balance is 12000. Daily loading is 2200 wagons and loaded receipt is 1600 wagons. If the ineffective wagons are 200, the WTR of the zone is... जोनल वैगन बैलस १२००० है। दैिनक लोिडंग २२०० वैगन है और लोडेड रसीद १६०० वैगन है। यिद इनइफे क्टव वैगन २०० ह, तो ज़ोन का WTR है......"	3.1 days	3.15 days	3.21 days	None of these	
What was the originating freight loading achieved by IR in FY 24 /25 ? िवत्त वष 24 / 25 म भारतीय रेल ारा मूल माल लदान िकतना था ?	Approx.1700 million tonnes	Approx. 1500 million tonnes	Approx. 1617 million tonnes	Approx. 1650 million tonnes	
"On a panel, EURRB button is used for….. एक पैनल पर, ई यु आर आर बी बटन का उपयोग िकसके िलए िकया जाता है?"	Partial route cancellation	Emmergency route cancellation	Reversal of points	Simultaneous reception	
What is the limit of validity of BPC for an ordinary Mail/Express train running with ICF coaches ? आईसीएफ कोचो ंके साथ चलने वाली साधारण मेल/एक्सप्रेस टेन के िलए बीपीसी की वैधता की सीमा ा है?	3000 Km	4000 Km	3500 Km	5000 Km	
Shunting operations shall be controlled by which means ? शंिटंग परचालन को िकस माध्यम से िनयंित्रत िकया जाएगा?	Verbal directions	Hand signals	Shunt signals	All of these	
A freight trains was stabled in examination yard for 18 hours after examination. Is the BPC valid ? एक मालगाड़ी को कै रज एंड वैगन परीक्षण के बाद १८ घंटे तक परीक्षण याड म खड़ा रखा गया। ा बी.पी.सी. वैध है?	"No , if it is CC rake"	"No, if it is premium rake"	Yes	No	
What is MSDAC ? एमएसडीएसी ा है?	Multi Section Digital Axle Counter	Modern Safe Data Analysis Counter	Modified Safe Digital Axle Counter	Modified Signal Data Analysis Center	
Which of the following is a 3 tier AC sleeper coach ? िनम्निलखत म से कौन सा ३ िटयर एसी ीपर कोच है?	WGSCN	WGACCN	WFACEN	WGACCW	
Which of the following commodities is permitted to be carried in containers? िनम्निलखत म से िकस वस्तु को कं टेनर म ले जाने की अनुमित है?	Coal for powerhouses	Fly Ash	Iron Ore	Imported coal	
"In operating statistics, which of the following is a derived unit? परचालन सांख्यकी म, िनम्निलखत म से कौन सी िडराइव्ड यूिनट है?"	Tonne-kms	Passenger kilometres	Engine hours	Earning per passenger kilometre	
When was the Official Language Act enacted? राजभाषा अिधिनयम कब लागू िकया गया?	"January 26, 1950"	"April 10, 1965"	"May 10, 1963"	"April 10, 1963"	
Which is not included in the eighth schedule of constitution? संिवधान की आठवी ंअनुसूची म कौन सी भाषा शािमल नही ंहै?	Bodo	Sindhi	Bhojpuri	Kashmiri	
Under which article of the Constitution it shall be the duty of the Union to promote the spread of the Hindi language ? संिवधान के िकस अनुेद के तहत िहंदी भाषा के प्रसार को बढ़ावा देना संघ का कतव्य होगा?	Article 351	Article 356	Article 244	Article 365	
Which medal is awarded to a General Manager for efforts made in the spread and use of Rajbhasha? राजभाषा के प्रसार और प्रयोग म िकए गए प्रयासो ंके िलए महाप्रबंधक को कौन सा पदक प्रदान िकया जाता है?	Kamalapati Tripathi Rajbhasha Swarna Padak	Rail Mantri Rajbhasja Rajat Padak	Maithilisharan Gupt Puraskar	Premchand Puraskar	
Who is the Chairperson of Railway Hindi Salahkaar Samiti? रेलवे िहंदी सलाहकार सिमित के अध्यक्ष कौन ह?	Hon. MR	Hon.MoS	CRB	DG HR	
When was the Committee of Parliament on Official Language constituted? राजभाषा पर संसदीय सिमित का गठन कब िकया गया था?	1963	1971	1973	1976	
"What is the name of the award scheme of Ministry of Railways, for fiction/story, novel, drama and other prose literature? कथा/कहानी, उपन्यास, नाटक और अन्य गद्य सािहत्य के िलए रेल मंत्रालय की पुरार योजना का नाम ा है?"	Maithilisharan Gupt award scheme	Rajbhasha individual cash award scheme	Premchand award scheme	Lal Bahadur Shastri technical original writing award scheme	
"Which state is included under ""Ga"" region for the implementation of official language policy? राजभाषा नीित के कायान्वयन के िलए ""ग"" क्षेत्र के अंतगत कौन सा राज्य शािमल है?"	Uttarakhand	Punjab	West Bengal	Maharashtra	
"Under which section of the Official Language Act, 1963 the Ministry of Railways has the legal obligation to use both English and Hindi for resolutions, general orders, rules, notifications, administrative reports etc.? राजभाषा अिधिनयम, 1963 की िकस धारा के तहत रेल मंत्रालय को प्रस्तावो,ं सामान्य आदेशो,ं िनयमो,ं अिधसूचनाओ,ं प्रशासिनक रपोट आिद के िलए अंग्रेजी और िहंदी दोनो ंका उपयोग करने का कानूनी दाियत्व है?"	Section 7	section 5	section 3(3)	section 4	
The Central Hindi Committee is chaired by… क द्रीय िहंदी सिमित की अध्यक्षता…करते हI	Hon. Prime Minister	Hon. Home Minister	Hon. Defence Minister	Hon. Vice President	
A Railway servant may be placed under suspension when.... िकसी रेलवे कमचारी को िनलत िकया जा सकता है जब…	disciplinary proceeding against him is contemplated	disciplinary proceeding against him is pending	"case against him in respect of any criminal offence, is under investigation"	All of these	
Which is not a minor penalty as per DAR ? अनुशासन एवं अपील िनयमो ंके अनुसार िनम्न म से कौन सा लघु दंड नही ंहै?	Withholding of increments for failure to pass departmental examination	Censure	Withholding of the Privilege Passes	Recovery from pay of any pecuniary loss caused	
Foreign Service means service in which a railway servant receives pay with sanction of government from…. फॉरेन सिवस से तात्पय ऐसी सेवा से है िजसम रेलवे कमचारी सरकार की मंजूरी से….. से वेतन प्राप्त करता है।	Foreign govrnment	Foreign corporations	Foreign railways	Any source other than the consolidated fund of India or state or UT	
"A monthly grant made to a railway servant who is not in receipt of pay or leave-salary is called…. िकसी रेलवे कमचारी को, जो वेतन या छुी-वेतन प्राप्त नही ंकर रहा है, िदया जाने वाला मािसक अनुदान कहलाता है…"	Subsistence grant	Compensatory allowance	Ex gratia	Special pay	
A railway service post carrying the pay in the pay matrix at level 11 will be classified as…. वेतन मैिटक्स म स्तर ११ पर वेतन वाले रेलवे सेवा पद को …. वगकृ त िकया जाएगा I	Gr. C	Gr. B Gaz.	Gr. A Gaz.	Gr. D	
Recruitment to Group A service in Railways can be through …. रेलवे म ग्रुप ए सेवा म भत ...के माध्यम से हो सकती है।	Competitive examination held by UPSC	Promotion of officers in Group B service	Transfer of an officer in the service of the government	All of these	
Procedure for imposing Major Penalties is prescribed in Rule …. of DAR. दीघ दारोपण की प्रिया अनुशासन एवं अपील िनयमो ंके िनयम….. अनुसार िनधारत है I	5	9	10	11	
No Railway servant shall be granted leave of any kind for a continuous period exceeding….years. िकसी भी रेलवे कमचारी को लगातार…. साल से अिधक अविध के िलए िकसी भी प्रकार की छुी नही ंदी जाएगी।	5	3	4	2	
"At the Railway Board level, the Personnel department is headed by ….. रेलवे बोड स्तर पर कािमक िवभाग का नेतृत्व .... ारा िकया जाता है।"	"Secretary, Railway Board"	Member(Staff )	DG(HR)	Establishment Officer	
The Doctrine of Pleasure is contained in Article…. Of the Constitution of India. प्रसाद का िसद्धांत (डॉक्टन ऑफ ेज़र) भारत के संिवधान के अनुेद .. म िनिहत है।	310(1)	311	356	365	
Who is the chairperson of PNM at the zonal level? झोनल स्तर पर पीएनएम का अध्यक्ष कौन है?	PCPO	AGM	GM	DGM(G)	
The amount of subscription payable towards Provident Fund for any particular year is capped at Rs….Lakh. िकसी वष के िलए भिवष्य िनिध के िलए देय अंशदान की रािश रु. ...लाख तक सीिमत है।	10	12	6	5	
Which conduct rule requires every railway servant to maintain absolute integrity at all times? कौन सा आचरण िनयम प्रत्येक रेलवे कमचारी को हर समय पूण सत्यिना बनाए रखने की अपेक्षा रखता है?	Rule 3(1)(i)	Rule 3(1)(ix)	Rule 3(1)(vi)	Rule 3(1)(x)	
Which conduct rule prohibits Railway servant to give or take or abet the giving or taking of dowry? कौन सा आचरण िनयम रेलवे कमचारी को दहेज देने या लेने या देने या लेने के िलए उकसाने पर रोक लगाता है?	Rule 13a (i)	Rule 3(1)(ix)	Rule 3c(1)	Rule 5	
"Where the distance between the old headquarters and the new headquarters is more than 1000 km, joining time admissible is ….days. जहां पुराने मुख्यालय और नए मुख्यालय के बीच की दूरी 1000 िकमी से अिधक है, वहां कायभार ग्रहण करने का समय ….िदन है।"	12	10	15	30	
Traffic Costing Office provides the data for…. टैिफक कॉस्टंग कायालय िनम्निलखत के िलए डेटा प्रदान करता है...	Seeking budetary support	Increasing profits	Profitability analysis for traffic	Minimization of social obligation	
"Under which article of the Constitution is the Consolidated Fund of India estabished? संिवधान के िकस अनुेद के तहत “भारत की संिचत िनिध"" स्थािपत की गई है?"	264	266(1)	356	270	
"The financial powers of the government, which have not been delegated to a subordinate authority, vest in….. सरकार की िवत्तीय शक्तयां, जो िकसी अधीनस्थ प्रािधकारी को नही ंसौपं ी गई ह, .... म िनिहत ह।"	Finance Ministry	RBI	CAG	Lok Sabha	
Which departments are responsible for contracts with siding owners? साइिडंग मािलको ंके साथ अनुबंध के िलए कौन से िवभाग िजम्मेदार ह?	Operating and Commercial	Engineering and Commercial	Operating and Engineering	Engineering and Accounts	
"In the context of contracts, what is EPC ? कॉैक्ट के सन्दभ म ई पी सी ा है ?"	Enginnering Procurement Construction	Engineering Production Consultancy	Emergeny Procurement Contract	Essential Property Contract	
Who represents the CAG of India in a Railway Zone? रेलवे जोन म भारत के सी ए जी का प्रितिनिधत्व कौन करता है?	PFA	Accountant General	PDA	None of the	
"In railway finance, EBR means… रेलवे िवत्त म, ई बी आर का मतलब है..."	Extended Budgetary Resource	Extra Budgetary Resources	Expected Budgetary Resource	Established Budget Rules	
"The report of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India presented to the parliament, is taken up for consideration by…. भारत के िनयंत्रक एवं महालेखा परीक्षक की संसद म प्रस्तुत रपोट पर….ारा िवचार िकया जाता हैI"	Standing Committee on Railways	Railway Convention Committee	Public Accounts Committee	JPC constituted by the Speaker	
Who is the budget officer of a Zone? िकसी जोन का बजट अिधकारी कौन होता है?	PCCM	PCE	PFA	GM	
All charges for maintenance and repairs after opening of the line for Traffic are allocated to… यातायात के िलए लाइन खुलने के बाद रखरखाव और मरम्मत के सभी शुल्क…..को आवंिटत िकए जाते हैI	Revenue	Capital	EBR(IF)	EBR(IRFC)	
What is the full-form of IRFC? आईआरएफसी का पूण रूप ा है?	International Railway Funding Corporation	Indian Railway Finance Corporation	Integrated Railway Finance Committee	Indian Railway Funding Company	
Who is the Plan Head Coordinator for PH 42 works? पीएच 42 काय के िलए योजना प्रमुख समन्वयक कौन है?	PCEE	PCCM	PCOM	PCME	
BOLT stands for…. बी ओ एल टी का मतलब है...	Borrow Open Lease Transfer	Build Operate Lease Transfer	Buy Own Lease Transfer	Build Own Lend Terminate	
Which is the Plan Head for Traffic Facility Works? यातायात सुिवधा काय के िलए कौन सा ान हेड है?	PH 64	PH 32	PH 16	PH 53	
GFR stands for…. जीएफआर का मतलब है…	Green Fuel Rules	General Finance Reserve	Green Finance Rating	General Financial Rules	
